Finding Aid for the Theodore Payne Papers LSC.2368
UCLA Library Special Collections
Theodore Payne papers
1879-1988
1903-1962
UCLA Library Special Collections
Theodore Payne Foundation for Wild Flowers and Native Plants, Incorporated
Payne, Theodore, 1872-1963
LSC.2368
58.75 linear feet (62 boxes, 2 cartons, 19 flat boxes, 21 shoe boxes)
Theodore Payne was a horticulturalist, nurseryman, and expert on California native plants. Materials in the Theodore Payne papers include personal and business records, records pertaining to his professional interests and activities, photographic material, publications on horticulture and gardening, landscaping records, Payne's writings and speeches, herbarium specimens, and artifacts.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials are not currently available for access and will require further processing and assessment. If you have questions about this material please email spec-coll@library.ucla.edu.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Theodore Payne Foundation for Wild Flowers and Native Plants, Inc., 2018.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9988899903606533
Biographical History
Theodore Payne (1872-1963) was a horticulturalist, nurseryman, and expert on California native plants. He was born in 1872 in Church Brampton, Northamptonshire, England. He moved to California in 1893 and owned and operated a nursery in Los Angeles from 1903 through 1960.
Theodore Payne's education started at Ackworth Academy, a Quaker boarding school in West York, England. In 1888 Theodore Payne apprenticed with J. Cheal & Sons for training in the nursery and seed business. John Cheal was a horticulturist, offering a full line of services, and Payne spent time in each of the departments, learning all elements of the nursery business.
In 1893, Payne began working as head gardener at the ranch of Madame Helena Modjeska, a stage actress located in Santiago Canyon, Orange County. In 1896 Theodore Payne moved to Los Angeles and obtained a position at Germain Fruit and Seed Company as a flower seedsman. Before opening his own nursery, Payne traveled to England and Europe, including Germany and France. On his travels he made contacts with several nurseries and maintained many of those relationships throughout his career. In 1903, Theodore Payne purchased Evans nursery at 440 South Broadway, Los Angeles. The Payne Nursery offered a variety of plants, seeds, and bulbs, as well as landscaping services. Two years later the Payne Nursery moved the office to 345 South Main Street and stayed there until 1931 when he moved his nursery to Los Feliz Blvd. In 1907 Payne married Alice Noyes, and they remained married for 56 years, until Theodore Payne's death.
Throughout his career as a nurseryman, Payne kept active with community outreach and education. He taught horticulture and gardening in many schools around the Los Angeles area and planted educational gardens on school grounds. He was also an active member of many committees and clubs, among them the Southern California Academy of Sciences and the board for Rancho Santa Ana Botanic Garden. Payne was also contracted on many jobs for state and federal projects, and acted as an advisor for maintaining California's native landscape. He actively researched native plants throughout his life and became an expert on the subject. In order to continue his life's work, he worked to start a foundation dedicated to the preservation and promotion of native plants of California. Although he first started working toward setting up a foundation in the early 1940s, it did not come into fruition until the late 1950s. He worked on the foundation and other endeavors relating to native plants up until his death. Theodore Payne died May 6, 1963 at 91 years old.
Scope and Contents
The Theodore Payne papers consists of records created or collected by Payne during the course of his life and career. Materials include personal papers, business records, records pertaining to his professional interests and activities, photographs, lantern slides, glass plate negatives, publications on horticulture and gardening, landscaping records, drafts and final publications of Payne's writings and speeches, and herbarium specimens and other artifacts belonging to Payne.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged in the following series:
Series 1: Personal materials, 1892-1964
Series 2: Professional materials, 1907-1969
Subseries 2.1: Correspondence
Subseries 2.2: Writings and presentations
Subseries 2.3: Associations and committees
Subseries 2.4: Consultations
Subseries 2.5: Research notes
Subseries 2.6: Reference files
Subseries 2.7: Awards
Subseries 2.8: Nursery-related books
Series 3: Theodore Payne Nursery records, 1907-1962
Subseries 3.1: Administrative records
Subseries 3.2: Correspondence
Subseries 3.3: Public relations
Subseries 3.4: Nursery catalogs
Subseries 3.5: Horticulture
Subseries 3.6: Seed sales books
Series 4: Project files, 1914-1961
Series 5: Artifacts, undated
Series 6: Photographs, slides, and film, 1893-1988
Series 7: Correspondence, 1906-1963
Series 8: Books, 1879-1962
Series 9: Nursery catalogs, 1895-1969
Horticulture -- California; Native plants for cultivation -- California; Theodore Payne Foundation for Wild Flowers and Native Plants, Incorporated; Payne, Theodore, 1872-1963 -- Archives
- Personal materials, 1892-1964; Series 1. (Box 1, Box 2, Box 49)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains material from Theodore Payne's personal life. These records include financial records, legal documents, correspondence, photographs, and postcards. Items include a diary belonging to his mother, personal correspondence between his family and friends, photographs and correspondence regarding his 80th birthday, and condolences to his wife, Alice, after Payne's death.
- Professional materials, 1907-1969; Series 2.
  This series covers Theodore Payne's professional activities, not directly related to his nursery. Included are Payne's plant research and identification, educational outreach, speeches, writings for articles and books, and Payne's participation in a wide range of clubs and associations in the greater Los Angeles area, Santa Barbara, and Orange County. Materials in this series cover topics such as the history of California horticulture, advocacy in saving native habitats and plants, urban development in the Los Angeles area, and narratives on changing the landscape and the increasing difficulty of finding plants in the wild.
  - Correspondence, Sub-Series 2.1. (Box 3)
    This subseries comprises letters regarding Payne's participation in the preservation of and education about California's native plants. The subseries contains information on speeches and educational programs that Payne conducted. There is also a large amount of material concerning California's changing landscape and the identification of plant species as well as their history. There are many letters from botanists and horticulturalists at universities, botanical gardens, state and federal departments, and museums asking Payne for information on California plants. There are a few letters of note in this series from California governors, botanist Kate Sessions, suffragist Sarah Bard Field, and a poem from Edna St. Vincent Millay
  - Writings and presentations, Subseries 2.2. (Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6)
    This subseries includes drafts for Theodore Payne's books: Life on the Modjeska Ranch; Adventures Among the Southern California Plants; and Brief History of a Life in Horticulture. There are also writings promoting wildflowers, native plants, eucalyptus, and other specialty plants; and a few drafts and note cards for speeches on the same topics. Most of the writing and speech topics relate to the value of wildflowers and native plants, and how to use them in gardens and landscapes.
  - Associations and committees, Subseries 2.3. (Box 6, Box 7, Box 8, Box 9, Box 10)
    This subseries consists of material from the various Southern California clubs and associations Payne participated in, including the Arboricultural Association, the Audubon Society, Rancho Santa Ana Botanic Garden, Southern California Academy of Sciences, and the Theodore Payne Foundation. His work in these groups ranged from advocacy against destruction of native landscapes, educational outreach, promoting native plants in gardens, and educational programs. Materials include association publications, correspondence, speech drafts, meeting notes, and reports. There are also significant materials dealing with environmental preservation issues for Griffith Park and Hancock Park.
  - Consultations, Subseries 2.4. (Box 10, Box 11)
    Materials in this subseries cover Payne's activities as a consultant for individuals, government offices, universities, and local associations. Payne consulted on topics such as landscaping, native plant education, and other horticultural topics. Significant topics are a survey on the Mediterranean fruit fly, the 1932 Olympic Beautification Project, and Rancho Santa Ana Botanic Garden.
  - Research notes, Subseries 2.5. (Box 11, Box 12)
    This subseries is comprised of materials created by Payne, as he researched various topics in horticulture and botany. Materials include correspondence on specific topics, notes, unpublished writings, and experiment records. There are research notes on plant climates and habitats, specimen identification, planting instructions, lists and categories of plants, and an essay titled, "Historical Horticultural Notes."
  - Reference files, Subseries 2.6. (Box 12, Box 13, Box 14, Box 15, Box 16, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 22, Box 23)
    This subseries contains material published or created by people other than Theodore Payne. Materials include gardening magazines, nursery catalogs, informational pamphlets, scientific publications, travel brochures, and publications from associations and conferences. Topics include eucalyptus, California native plants, agriculture, and gardening. Items include state and national park publications, Western Shade Tree publications, several issues of Flora and Sylva (1904, 1905), Sylva of California (1910), several issues of Gardener's Chronicle (1897–1927), and several issues of Rural Californian. Boxes 16-18 hold a card index of plant related books listed in alphabetical order by author.
  - Awards, Subseries 2.7. (Box 14, Folder 7-8, Box 21, Box 24, Box 25)
    This subseries includes awards and recognitions Payne received during his lifetime. There is also a folder containing written lists of honors and awards received by Payne.
  - Nursery-related books, Subseries 2.8. (Box 27, Box 28, Box 29, Box 30, Box 32)
    This subseries contains nursery and plant-related books, pamphlets, and bulletins published from 1901-1979. Box 32 includes Pacific Garden and Eucalypts of Australia.
- Theodore Payne Nursery records, 1907-1962; Series 3.
  This series comprises records created by Payne's nursery for all activities.
  - Administrative records, Subseries 3.1. (Box 20, Box 33, Box 49)
    This subseries contains records that support the administrative functions of the Theodore Payne Nursery. Materials include licenses and permits, leases, patents and copyrights, information for investors, and a plot plans for the Theodore Payne Nursery at 2969 Los Feliz Boulevard.
  - Nursery Correspondence, Subseries 3.2. (Box 33, Box 34, Box 35, Box 50, Box 51, Box 52)
    This subseries includes mail orders and other communications from prominent botanical gardens and nurseries from the East Coast, England, France, Holland, South Africa, Japan, Australia, and Latin America. It also provides information about the organizations and causes to which Theodore Payne donated seeds and plants. Also included is correspondence about planting instructions, customer interactions, and general horticulture advice. There are also four hardbound volumes of correspondence.
  - Financial records, 3.3. (Box 21, Box 23, Box 35, Box 36, Box 37, Box 38, Box 39)
    This subseries contains inventories, invoices, shipping receipts, banking information, tax records, ledgers, price lists, and receipts. All records pertaining to Theodore Payne's bankruptcy have been placed in a discrete series. Payne appears to have gathered these documents together, most likely for reference in his prolonged struggle. Materials in this series include letters of recommendation, information for investors, financial documents, bank records, court documents, and letters and articles written by Payne. Documents date from around 1930 to 1940.
  - Public relations, Subseries 3.4. (Box 31, Box 39, Box 40, Box 41, Box 42, Box 43, Box 44)
    This subseries contains material relating to the promotion and marketing of the Theodore Payne Nursery. Other materials include seed packets and other packaging; mailing and contact lists; advertisements, informational pamphlets, and flyers; and information on flower shows in which Payne participated.
  - Theodore Payne Nursery catalogs, 1904-1956; Subseries 3.5. (Box 44, Box 45, Box 46)
    This subseries contains the Theodore Payne Nursery catalogs filed in chronological order: Box 44: 1904-1916; Box 45:1917-1930; Box 46: 1931-1956 and two undated catalogs.
  - Horticulture, Subseries 3.6. (Box 20, Box 46, Box 47)
    This subseries contains propagation journals, planting plans for the nursery, seed mix recipes, notes on stock, seed collecting data, herbarium of 18 samples, and notes on the plant species, Lupinus Paynei.
  - Seed sales books, Subseries 3.7. (Box 48)
    This subseries contains two books labeled Nursery Sales and Seed Sales from 1955-1959.
- Project files, 1914-1961; Series 4. (Box 53, Box 54, Box 55, Box 56)
  This series contains material pertaining to the design, construction, and planting of landscape projects. Materials include price quotes, records of labor, planning notes, reports, and drawn plans. Also included are the landscaping plans for the Pratt House by Greene and Greene and the Mosk House by Richard Neutra. Box 53 includes Landscape Project Invoices, Miscellaneous Projects A-Z and named projects Ainley - Burhaus. Box 54 includes projects California Institute of Technology - Fantou. Box 55 includes projects Farnham - Loomis. Box 56 includes projects Los Angeles, City of - Williams, Wayne.
- Artifacts, undated; Series 5. (Box 25, Box 57, Box 58, Box 59, Box 60)
  This series consists of three-dimensional objects such as wallets, a camera, seed and wood samples, a trophy, and some personal items belonging to Theodore Payne.
- Photographs, slides, and film, 1893-1988; Series 6.
  This series is comprised of photographs, slides, and film. Formats include lantern slides, glass plate negatives, and 8mm film reels.
  - Photographs (Box 20, Box 47, Folder 13, Box 61, Box 62, Box 63, Box 64, Box 65, Box 66, Box 67, Box 68, Box 69, Box 70, Box 71, Box 72, Box 82)
    Large portions of the photographs are of plant specimens used for nursery catalogs or for plant identification. Other photographs cover a wide range of subjects including a portrait of Theodore Payne and views of the street entrance of the Payne Nursery and the Los Angeles area in the early 20th century.
  - Slides and Color Glass Plates (Box 73, Box 74, Box 75, Box 76, Box 77, Box 78, Box 79, Box 80)
    This subseries contains glass plate negatives, box 72; photographic slides, box 73; and color glass plates, boxes 75 and 76. The plates in box 76 are identified as W. Scott Lewis and numbered.
  - Film, 8 video recordings (8 unprocessed 8mm film reels) (Box 81)
    This subseries contains 8mm film reels.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    CONTAINS UNPROCESSED AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Materials will require assessment and may need further processing for safe access. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
- Correspondence, 1906-1963; Series 7. (Box 82, Box 83, Box 84, Box 85)
  This series is comprised of correspondence topics found in all other series.
  Box 82: Correspondence Received 1941-1954
  Box 83: Correspondence Received 1955-1957
  Box 84: Correspondence Received 1959-1963.
  Box 85: Envelopes of client correspondence addressed to Theodore Payne.
- Books, 1879-1962; Series 8.; 2.0 linear feet
  This series contains books about plants, trees, and flowers.
  - Who's who in California, 1962 (Box 87)
  - Story of Carmelita and its trees, 1928 (Box 87)
  - Trees and shrubs of California gardens, 1926 (Box 87)
  - Australian rain-forest trees, 1929 (Box 87)
  - New World Cypresses, 1948 (Box 87)
  - Know your own trees, 1942 (Box 86)
  - Tumba of Torrey Pines, 1931 (Box 86)
  - William Andrew Spalding: Los Angeles newspaperman, 1961 (Box 86)
  - How plants are trained to work for man: volume I, plant breeding, 1921 (Box 86)
  - How plants are trained to work for man: volume II, grafting and budding, 1921 (Box 86)
  - How plants are trained to work for man: volume III, fruit improvement, 1921 (Box 86)
  - How plants are trained to work for man: volume IV, small fruits, 1921 (Box 86)
  - How plants are trained to work for man: volume V, gardening, 1921 (Box 86)
  - How plants are trained to work for man: volume VI, useful plants, 1921 (Box 86)
  - How plants are trained to work for man: volume VII, flowers, 1921 (Box 86)
  - How plants are trained to work for man: volume VIII, trees, biography, index, 1921 (Box 86)
  - California garden flowers, 1914 (Box 86)
  - Camellia culture, 1958 (Box 86)
  - Henderson's handbook of plants and general horticulture, 1910 (Box 86)
  - Ceanothus, 1942 (Box 86)
  - Conspicuous California plants with notes on their garden uses, 1938 (Box 86)
  - With the flowers and trees in California, 1914 (Box 87)
  - Flora of Los Angeles and vicinity, 1917 (Box 87)
  - Gardening in California, 1904 (Box 87)
  - Summary of the culture of California plants at the Rancho Santa Ana Botanic Garden 1927-1950, 1957 (Box 87)
  - Planting lists for southern California, a handbook of ornamental plants, 1933 (Box 87)
  - Practical fruit culture, a treatise on planting, growing, storage, etc., of hardy fruits for market and private growers, 1892 (Box 87)
  - Naturalist's directory, 1914 (Box 87)
  - Research on the Eucalypts, especially in regard to their essential oils, 1902 (Box 87)
  - Descriptive atlas of the eucalypts of Australia and the adjoining islands, 1879 (Box 87)
- Nursery catalogs, 1895-1969; Series 9.
  This series contains nursery catalogs about plants from all over the world.
  - Seeds from the South Pacific, 1961-1962; Dow, Peter B. and Company (Box 88)
  - General Catalogue of Choice Nursery Stock, 1929; Duncan & Davies Ltd. (Box 88)
  - Complete Catalogue, 1955 Season; Duncan & Davies Ltd. (Box 88)
  - New Zealand Native Trees, Shrubs, Plants, Ferns and Seeds, 1925 May; Duncan & Davies Ltd. (Box 88)
  - Seed, Bulb, Plant & Fruit Tree Catalogue, 1935; Law, Somner & Co. (Box 88)
  - Special Trade Price List, 1931 June 1; Law, Somner Pty. Ltd. (Box 88)
  - Special Trade Price List, 1939 July 1; Law, Somner, Pry. Ltd. (Box 88)
  - Descriptive Catalogue of Australian Timber Tree Seeds, 1926; Murphy, Andrew (Box 88)
  - Descriptive Catalogue of Australian Timber Tree Seeds, 1928-1929; Murphy, Andrew (Box 88)
  - Price List of Trees and Shrubs, 1960; New South Wales Forestry Commission Tree Nurseries (Box 88)
  - Australian Native Plants, 1948-1949; Nindethana Nursery (Box 88)
  - Everything for the Garden, 1916; Searl & Sons (Box 88)
  - Catalogue, 1903 March; P.L.C. Shepherd & Son (Box 88)
  - Catalogue, 1910-1911; P.L.C. Shepherd & Son (Box 88)
  - Catalogue and Garden Guide, 1913; P.L.C. Shepherd & Son (Box 88)
    86th Edition
  - Catalogue of Seeds and Plants, 1908; Staer, J. & Co. (Box 88)
  - Descriptive Catalogue of Seeds, Plants and Bulbs, 1937-1938; The Chugai Nursery Co. (Box 88)
  - Descriptive Catalogue of Seeds, Plants and Bulbs, 1940-1941; The Chugai Nursery Co. (Box 88)
  - Catalogue of Sikkim Himalayan, 1930; The Chandra Nursery (Box 88)
  - Chrysanthemums, 1938 Autumn-1939 Spring; Seikoen (Box 88)
  - What, When, How to Plant… and Where, undated; A & M Reliable Seeds (Box 89)
    Bulletin No. 20
  - California Wildflowers, undated; A & M Reliable Seeds (Box 89)
    Bulletin No. 21
  - Catalog, 1929; Aggeler & Musser Seed Co. (Box 89)
    Thirty Sixth Annual Catalog
  - Wholesale List of Bulbs, 1932 Autumn; Aggeler & Musser Seed Co. (Box 89)
  - Catalog, 1935; Aggeler & Musser Seed Co. (Box 89)
    Forty Second Annual Catalog
  - Seeds Garden and Farm Supplies, 1944; Aggeler & Musser Seed Co. (Box 89)
    51st Annual Catalog
  - Seeds Garden and Farm Supplies, 1947; Aggeler & Musser Seed Co. (Box 89)
    54th Annual Catalog
  - Seeds Garden and Farm Supplies, 1950-51; Aggeler & Musser Seed Co. (Box 89)
  - Seeds Garden and Farm Supplies… Planting Information, 1955; Aggeler & Musser Seed Co. (Box 89)
    62nd Annual Catalog
  - Catalog, 1933; Armstrong Nurseries (Box 89)
  - Catalog, 1935; Armstrong Nurseries (Box 89)
  - Catalog, 1937; Armstrong Nurseries (Box 89)
  - 1939-1940 Wholesale Price List Roses and Ornamentals, 1939 June 1; Armstrong Nurseries (Box 89)
  - Catalog, 1954; Armstrong Nurseries (Box 89)
  - Catalog, 1954 Fall-1955 Spring; Armstrong Nurseries (Box 89)
  - Now! It's Rose Planting Time, 1962; Armstrong Nurseries (Box 89)
  - Catalog, 1962; Armstrong Nurseries (Box 89)
  - Wholesale Rose Catalog, 1962-1963; Armstrong Nurseries (Box 89)
  - Wholesale Ornamental Price List, 1963; Armstrong Nurseries (Box 89)
  - Catalog, undated; Burbank, Luther (Box 89)
  - The New Agricultural-Horticultural Opuntias, 1907 June 1; Burbank, Luther (Box 89)
  - Twentieth Century Fruits, 1911-1912; Burbank, Luther (Box 89)
  - The Gold Medal Newest Agricultural-Horticultural Opuntias, 1912 May 1; Burbank, Luther (Box 89)
  - Fruits, Flowers and Various Economic Plants, 1918; Burbank, Luther (Box 89)
  - New Creations and Special New Selections in Seeds, 1918; Burbank, Luther (Box 89)
  - Seeds - 1922, Burbank, Luther (Box 89)
  - Seed Buyers Guide, 1961 Summer; Carter, Roy Seedsman (Box 90)
  - Extremely Rare Native Bulbs of the West, 1958; Roy Silvear (Box 90)
    Loose sheet
  - Extremely Rare Native Bulbs of the West, 1958; Roy Silvear (Box 90)
  - California Grown Bulbs, 1932 August 15; Clarke, W.B. & Son (Box 90)
  - Forest Seeds of California, undated; R.S. Adams & A.P. Baal (Box 90)
  - Loose Sheet Price List, 1957; O. Kenneth Smith (Box 90)
  - Street Trees Available for Planting, 1957 July 1; Saratoga Horticultural Foundation (Box 90)
  - Wholesale Price List, 1951; Elsie Cisler (Box 90)
  - Burpee Seeds, 1961; Burpee Co. (Box 90)
  - Ornamental and Fruit Trees, 1915; California Nursery Co. Inc. (Box 90)
  - Ornamental Trees and Plants, undated; California Nursery Co. Inc. (Box 90)
  - Wholesale List, 1939-1940 Season; California Roses, Inc. (Box 90)
  - Seed Buyer's Guide For Nurserymen, 1960-1961 Winter; Carter, Roy Seedsman (Box 90)
  - Seed Buyer's Guide for Commercial Growers, 1962; Carter, Roy Seedsman (Box 90)
  - Seed Buyer's Guide for Commercial Growers, 1963; Carter, Roy Seedsman (Box 90)
  - Garden Aristocrats, 1941; Clarke Nursery (Box 90)
    Volume 8
  - Wholesale Price List, 1939-1940 Season; Clarke, W.B. & Co. (Box 90)
  - Wholesale Price List, 1961-1962 Season; Clarke, W.B. & Co. (Box 90)
  - Wholesale Catalog to the trade, 1959-1960; Coates, Leonard Nurseries, Inc. (Box 90)
  - Price List of Fruit and Nut Trees, undated; Coates, Leonard Nurseries, Inc. (Box 90)
  - Wholesale List, 1959-1960 Season; Coolidge Gardens (Box 90)
  - Wholesale Price List, 1962-1963 Season; Deigaard Nurseries, Inc. (Box 90)